<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-21T23:31:41+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alyssa Lee</title><subtitle>My personal website </subtitle><entry><title type="html">I joined the Rutgers sailing team!</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/i-joined-ru-sailing-team/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I joined the Rutgers sailing team!"/><published>2025-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/i-joined-ru-sailing-team</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/i-joined-ru-sailing-team/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../../../assets/img/2025-09-21/boat.jpg" alt="internalimg" style="max-width:400px"/></p> <p>I joined the Rutgers sailing team! After leaving Williams-Mystic, I wasn’t sure if I’d get the chance to sail again. Lucky me, I ended up at a school with an awesome sailing team :) It’s pretty laid back if you aren’t competing, which is good for me as a beginner.</p> <p>I’ve been to a few practices so far, and last time I got to skipper! (That means I’m sitting in the back steering the boat, as you can see in the photo.) In the smaller one-person boats I sailed at Williams-Mystic, I did skipper, but this felt pretty different. I felt really clumsy trying to switch sides on the boat while also steering and adjusting the sail. I was starting to get the hang of it by the end though :)</p> <p>It’s a lot less stressful to be crew, which is the role of the second person in the boat (responsible for the smaller sail– the jib– while also moving around to keep the boat from tilting too far to one side). It’s still a challenge, though.</p> <p>I’m excited to keep going to practice and improving my sailing skills. Thanks to the experienced team members and coaches for helping me learn. It’s awesome!</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">science book dump!</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/science-book-dump/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="science book dump!"/><published>2025-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/science-book-dump</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/science-book-dump/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../../../assets/img/2025-09-21/everything-is-tuberculosis.jpg" alt="everything is tuberculosis book cover" style="max-width:250px"/> <img src="../../../assets/img/2025-09-21/crossings.jpg" alt="crossings book cover" style="max-width:250px"/> <img src="../../../assets/img/2025-09-21/blight.jpg" alt="blight book cover" style="max-width:250px"/></p> <h2 id="everything-is-tuberculosis-by-john-green"><em>Everything is Tuberculosis</em> by John Green</h2> <p>I am a huge fan of John Green as a novelist, as a science YouTuber, and as an activist. This book is a history of tuberculosis, humanity’s most deadly infectious disease for millennia, and how it has shaped human society. John Green writes with compassion, clarity, and optimism about why tuberculosis (a disease we know how to cure!) is still the leading cause of death by infectious disease today, and how we can choose to change that. He also partnered with my favorite science YouTube channel Kurzgesagt to make a <a href="https://youtu.be/GFLb5h2O2Ww?si=Gi_IMJEWrT23lrqL">video</a> about it.</p> <p>The scientific hurdles to eradicating tuberculosis are largely solved. What will rid us of tuberculosis is access to quality care for people everywhere in the world. This is not a problem for science to solve, but for society. As Albert Einstein wrote in 1949, “Science, however, cannot create ends and, even less, instill them in human beings; science, at most, can supply the means by which to attain certain ends.” That’s why I believe my responsibility as a scientist extends beyond creating knowledge. I also have a responsibility to ensure that scientific knowledge is used to benefit all people. John Green is the kind of person I aspire to be: a scientist-activist focused on making the world a better place.</p> <h2 id="crossings-how-road-ecology-is-shaping-the-future-of-our-planet-by-ben-goldfarb"><em>Crossings: How Road Ecology is Shaping the Future of Our Planet</em> by Ben Goldfarb</h2> <p><em>Crossings</em> was an entertaining and fascinating read! It tells the stories of people trying to protect wildlife from becoming roadkill, in a landscape crisscrossed everywhere by roads. Would recommend.</p> <h2 id="blight-fungi-and-the-coming-pandemic-by-emily-monosson"><em>Blight: Fungi and the Coming Pandemic</em> by Emily Monosson</h2> <p>This book was a little terrifying. Fungal diseases have caused catastrophic population decline in other species, from bats to bananas, but we haven’t seen a major fungal pandemic affecting humans. Yet.</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="biology"/><category term="books"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[tuberculosis, wildlife crossings, and scary fungi]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate change newsletters I like</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/climate-newsletters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate change newsletters I like"/><published>2025-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/climate-newsletters</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/climate-newsletters/"><![CDATA[<p>Are you looking for sources to read about climate change? Here, I recommend two independent news organizations and five Substacks.</p> <h3 id="inside-climate-news-news-site">Inside Climate News (<a href="https://insideclimatenews.org/">news site</a>)</h3> <p>Inside Climate News publishes local and national climate news stories. They are a nonprofit news organization and once won a Pulitzer for reporting on a Michigan oil spill.</p> <h3 id="grist-news-site">Grist (<a href="https://grist.org/">news site</a>)</h3> <p>Grist is another great nonprofit news organization reporting on climate change, with a focus on climate justice.</p> <h3 id="the-crucial-years-by-bill-mckibben-substack">The Crucial Years, by Bill McKibben (<a href="https://billmckibben.substack.com/">Substack</a>)</h3> <p>Bill McKibben is a longtime activist who founded climate activism groups 350.org and Third Act, a group for people 60 and older concerned about the climate. I liked <a href="https://billmckibben.substack.com/p/vandalism-with-a-plan">this recent article</a>, where he analyzes the current administration’s attacks on energy-saving measures such as Energy Star appliances (which saved consumers $14 billion in utility bills last year), alternatives to incandescent light bulbs, and low-flow shower heads, among other things. McKibben points out that “many things the Trump administration does are simply designed to waste energy” in an effort to prop up Big Oil in a world that is rapidly switching to more efficient clean energy sources.</p> <h3 id="heated-by-emily-atkin-substack">HEATED, by Emily Atkin (<a href="https://heated.world/">Substack</a>)</h3> <p>Emily Atkin on <a href="https://heated.world/about">why she writes HEATED</a>: “It is not your fault that the planet is burning. Your air conditioner, your hamburger, your gas-powered car—these aren’t the reasons we only have about a decade to prevent irreversible climate catastrophe. No; the majority of the blame for the climate emergency lies at the foot of the greedy […] <strong>It’s time to get angry.</strong>”</p> <p>I recommend her post <a href="https://heated.world/p/what-can-i-do-anything">“What can I do? Anything”</a> for suggestions on how any of us can contribute to stopping climate change– primarily by pushing for transformative changes to society, rather than changing individual choices.</p> <p>She also reported on <a href="https://heated.world/p/the-reality-of-hawaiis-tourist-climate">Hawaii’s recent passage of the “green fee”</a>, a small (0.75%) increase in the tax on tourist lodgings that will raise $100 million to protect Hawaii against hurricanes, wildfires, and coral reef loss. Hawaii has also filed a lawsuit against several major fossil fuel companies, seeking compensation for the damage caused by climate change. They are not the only state to do so. We’ll have to wait to see how this plays out in court.</p> <h3 id="talking-climate-by-katherine-hayhoe-substack">Talking Climate, by Katherine Hayhoe (<a href="https://www.talkingclimate.ca/">Substack</a>)</h3> <p>Katherine Hayhoe is a climate scientist and communicator. Every week, she posts a climate update including good news, bad news, and what you can do to help.</p> <p>In her most recent post (<a href="https://www.talkingclimate.ca/p/are-we-really-doomed">“Are we really doomed?”</a>), she rejects doomerism: the belief that we are already doomed to climate catastrophe, so we might as well just give up.</p> <p>Scare tactics and shaming aren’t effective strategies; they cause people to shut down, not act. “Instead, talk about why you care about climate change. How is it affecting the people, places, or things you love? […] Use your voice to advocate for change where you live, work, study, or worship.”</p> <h3 id="sustainability-by-numbers-by-hannah-ritchie-substack">Sustainability by Numbers, by Hannah Ritchie (<a href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/">Substack</a>)</h3> <p>Hannah Ritchie is a data scientist who writes about sustainability “not based on instincts, but on data.” She writes with clarity about complicated topics, where other sources might ignore the complex reality in favor of a straightforward narrative. She also works at <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/">Our World in Data</a>, a great resource for data on major world problems.</p> <h3 id="your-dose-of-climate-hope-by-climate-action-now-substack">Your Dose of Climate Hope, by Climate Action Now (<a href="https://climateactapp.substack.com/">Substack</a>)</h3> <p>This blog posts a hopeful story about climate change problem-solving every day, accompanied by a suggested action. Perfect for a quick read when you need some climate hope.</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you looking for sources to read about climate change? Here, I recommend two independent news organizations and five Substacks.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advice for starting your PhD</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/start-a-phd-advice-compilation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advice for starting your PhD"/><published>2025-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/start-a-phd-advice-compilation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/start-a-phd-advice-compilation/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m both excited to start my PhD and really nervous, because I want to get it right. So, I’ve been obsessively trawling the Internet looking for advice. Here’s what I’ve got:</p> <h3 id="take-charge">Take charge</h3> <p>Decide what you want out of your degree and go get it. “You had better decide early on that you are in charge of your program. <strong>The degree you get is yours to create.</strong>”<sup id="fnref:stearns"><a href="#fn:stearns" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p> <p>“Think of yourself as a professional, <strong>someone who will be a biologist for the rest of your life</strong>. Start to accumulate a library and reprint collection, develop a computerized list of references and addresses, attend meetings, meet with visiting seminar speakers, correspond with people working on related problems, send out copies of your articles as they are published, etc.”<sup id="fnref:reply-to-stearns"><a href="#fn:reply-to-stearns" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p> <h3 id="read-widely-and-learn-to-think-for-yourself">Read widely and learn to think for yourself</h3> <p>“When you first arrive, read and think widely and exhaustively for a year. <strong>Assume that everything you read is bullshit</strong> until the author manages to convince you that it isn’t.”<sup id="fnref:stearns:1"><a href="#fn:stearns" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p> <h3 id="attend-seminars">Attend seminars</h3> <p>Stanford math professor Ravi Vakil suggests that you write down three things you got out of each seminar. Keep it to only three things– if you find a fourth, you must cut one. This will help you <strong>focus on what <em>you</em> can get out of the talk</strong>, not necessarily what the speaker’s main points are.</p> <p>Some reasons why you should attend seminars<sup id="fnref:vakil"><a href="#fn:vakil" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>:</p> <ul> <li> <p>“Don’t be narrow and concentrate only on your particular problem. Learn things from all over the field, and beyond.”</p> </li> <li> <p>“Your thesis problem may well come out of an idea you have while sitting in a seminar. Go to seminar dinners when at all possible, even though it is scary, and no one else is going.”</p> </li> <li> <p>“Try to ask one question at as many seminars as possible, either during the talk, or privately afterwards. The act of trying to formulating an interesting question (for you, not the speaker!) is a worthwhile exercise, and can focus the mind.”</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="be-ready-to-change-course-if-needed">Be ready to change course if needed</h3> <p><strong>Things will go wrong</strong>– that’s a part of doing research. Don’t get upset when that happens; instead, include alternatives as part of the plan:</p> <p>“Write down a list of the major problems that could arise and ruin the whole project. Then write down a list of alternatives that you will do if things actually do go wrong. It is not a bad idea to design two or three projects and start them in parallel to see which one has the best practical chance of succeeding.”<sup id="fnref:stearns:2"><a href="#fn:stearns" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p> <h3 id="write-everything-down">Write everything down</h3> <p>“‘I don’t need to write that down, I’ll remember it’ is the biggest lie you can tell yourself! <strong>Write down everything you do — even if it doesn’t work.</strong> This includes meeting notes, method details, code annotations, among other things.”<sup id="fnref:20-things"><a href="#fn:20-things" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></p> <h3 id="write-papers-as-you-go">Write papers as you go</h3> <p>“Treat each project (even a literature review) as if it is potentially publishable.”<sup id="fnref:reply-to-stearns:1"><a href="#fn:reply-to-stearns" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p> <p>“Start a Word document called ‘Thesis’”.<sup id="fnref:ellie-wood"><a href="#fn:ellie-wood" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup></p> <p>“You do a lot of reading during your first year— <strong>write it up</strong>. One of the best research groups I collaborated with during my PhD had an initiative where all first year PhD students should try to publish a review article.”<sup id="fnref:savvy-scientist"><a href="#fn:savvy-scientist" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup></p> <h3 id="finished-is-better-than-perfect">Finished is better than perfect</h3> <p>“<strong>The best thesis is a finished thesis.</strong> No matter how much time you spend perfecting your first draft, your work will come back covered in corrections, and you will go through more drafts before you submit your final version. Send your drafts to your supervisor sooner rather than later.”<sup id="fnref:20-things:1"><a href="#fn:20-things" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></p> <h3 id="enjoy-it">Enjoy it!</h3> <p>“<strong>Enjoy your PhD!</strong> It can be tough, and there will be days when you wish you had a ‘normal’ job, but PhDs are full of wonderful experiences and give you the opportunity to work on something that fascinates you. Celebrate your successes and enjoy yourself.”<sup id="fnref:20-things:2"><a href="#fn:20-things" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:stearns"> <p><a href="https://stearnslab.yale.edu/modest-advice">Modest Advice, by Stephen C. Stearns</a> <a href="#fnref:stearns" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:stearns:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a> <a href="#fnref:stearns:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>3</sup></a></p> </li> <li id="fn:reply-to-stearns"> <p><a href="https://www.bio.fsu.edu/eerdg/pdfs/HueyAcynicalAdvice.pdf">Reply to Stearns, by Raymond B. Huey</a> <a href="#fnref:reply-to-stearns" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:reply-to-stearns:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p> </li> <li id="fn:vakil"> <p><a href="https://math.stanford.edu/~vakil/potentialstudents.html">For potential PhD students, by Ravi Vakil</a> <a href="#fnref:vakil" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:20-things"> <p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-07332-x">Twenty things I wish I’d known when I started my PhD, by Lucy A. Taylor</a> <a href="#fnref:20-things" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:20-things:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a> <a href="#fnref:20-things:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>3</sup></a></p> </li> <li id="fn:ellie-wood"> <p><a href="https://blogs.ed.ac.uk/ellie-wood/2020/09/04/five-tips-for-starting-and-continuing-a-phd/">Five tips for starting (and continuing) a PhD, by Ellie Wood</a> <a href="#fnref:ellie-wood" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:savvy-scientist"> <p><a href="https://www.thesavvyscientist.com/tips-for-new-phd-students/">Tips for New PhD Students, by The Savvy Scientist</a> <a href="#fnref:savvy-scientist" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="phd"/><category term="biology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A compilation]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Standing up for science</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/standing-up-for-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Standing up for science"/><published>2025-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/standing-up-for-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/standing-up-for-science/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I attended the Stand Up for Science protest in Chicago! The rally was part of a nationwide protest against the Trump administration’s science funding cuts. The <a href="https://standupforscience2025.org/our-policy-goals/">major policy goals</a> were to end censorship of science, secure federal science funding, and protect diversity and inclusion programs. It got <a href="https://abc7chicago.com/post/stand-science-rally-thousands-federal-plaza-chicago-oppose-trump-administration-research-funding-cuts/15989395/">local</a> and <a href="https://apnews.com/article/science-doctors-cuts-budget-trump-health-climate-cead2742a686b3dbc2fe4b1294939454">national</a> news coverage!</p> <p><img src="../../../assets/img/2025-03-07/stand-up-for-science-protest.png" alt="Photo of crowd at stand up for science protest" style="max-width:350px"/> <img src="../../../assets/img/2025-03-07/stand-up-for-science-sign.png" alt="Photo of handmade sign saying stand up for science" style="max-width:350px"/></p> <p>I was really excited to go and brought my own sign! It was my second protest ever. (My first one was the <a href="https://newsinteractive.post-gazette.com/climate-rally-in-oakland/">“Climate Can’t Wait” rally</a> in Pittsburgh <a href="https://www.wesa.fm/environment-energy/2025-02-08/pittsburgh-climate-rally-urge-local-action">last month</a>.)</p> <p>As a young scientist, I’m pretty uncertain about my career prospects right now. Even if the NIH funding cuts are reversed or a new administration restores science funding in four years, plenty of damage has already been done. It may take some time for scientific agencies and institutions to recover.</p> <p>I’m proud to be able to stand up for scientific research– not just for me, but for everyone who relies on vaccines, medicines, clean water, and all the other innumerable good things that come from federal science funding. Other than attending protests, spreading the word, and calling elected officials, I’ll keep following my own dream of being a scientist and hope that better times are to come.</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><category term="biology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I attended the Stand Up for Science protest in Chicago! The rally was part of a nationwide protest against the Trump administration’s science funding cuts. The major policy goals were to end censorship of science, secure federal science funding, and protect diversity and inclusion programs. It got local and national news coverage!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I’ve been reading to start 2025</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/reading-to-start-2025/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I’ve been reading to start 2025"/><published>2025-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/reading-to-start-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/reading-to-start-2025/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../../../assets/img/2025-01-12/book_covers.png" alt="book covers" style="max-width:800px"/></p> <h3 id="this-idea-must-die-scientific-theories-that-are-blocking-progress">This Idea Must Die: Scientific Theories That Are Blocking Progress</h3> <p>Edited by John Brockman, Edge.org</p> <p>Brief essays from an enormous variety of scholarly fields, on topics as diverse as quantum physics, the tragedy of the commons, cancer-causing mutations, free will, and p-values. Each one argues that a particular idea, like “the habitable zone” or “people are sheep”, should be discarded. Some of them directly contradict each other. My favorite essays take down common misconceptions about statistics, where many scientists (including myself) frequently encounter pitfalls.</p> <h3 id="the-song-of-the-cell">The Song of the Cell</h3> <p>by Siddhartha Mukherjee</p> <p>The history of cell biology, from the discovery of cells to today’s medical breakthroughs, narrated by talented writer/physician/researcher Siddhartha Mukherjee. I really like this one. Mukherjee tells anecdotes from his own life to complement the main story, which are often amusing, moving, or both.</p> <h3 id="project-hail-mary">Project Hail Mary</h3> <p>by Andy Weir</p> <p>I’ve written <a href="/blog/2024/scifi-book-recs/">before</a> about how much I enjoy Andy Weir, and this book was unexpectedly heartwarming. As always, the story is full of fascinating (sometimes fictional) scientific details. Also, it’s about aliens. Would recommend :)</p> <h3 id="the-light-eaters-how-the-unseen-world-of-plant-intelligence-offers-a-new-understanding-of-life-on-earth">The Light Eaters: How the Unseen World of Plant Intelligence Offers a New Understanding of Life on Earth</h3> <p>by Zoe Schlanger</p> <p>This book is beautiful! I love the way the author sees plants, as growing (haha) evidence indicates that plants are capable of making decisions, making sense of complex information, and other behaviors that resemble what we might call intelligence. One chapter that stuck with me was about a plant that can mimic the visual appearance of nearby leaves from <em>any</em> other plant, even ones that aren’t native to its area! How does it know what they look like??? Does it have <em>eyes</em>? Is it lifting genetic information from its neighbors’ bacteria? We don’t know (yet).</p> <h3 id="revenge-of-the-tipping-point">Revenge of the Tipping Point</h3> <p>by Malcolm Gladwell</p> <p>This book is about epidemics, whether viral (like COVID-19) or sociobehavioral (like bank robberies), and the factors that precipitate them. I have to remind myself to approach popular sociology books with a healthy dose of skepticism (it’s too easy to see what you want to see when diagnosing society’s ills). That said, <em>Revenge of the Tipping Point</em> is a thought-provoking and engaging read. Would recommend.</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="biology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Andy Weir, Siddhartha Mukherjee, Malcolm Gladwell, and more]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Donating for the climate in 2025</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/donations-for-climate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Donating for the climate in 2025"/><published>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/donations-for-climate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/donations-for-climate/"><![CDATA[<p>Happy New Year! Every January since I started making money, I’ve donated some of it. Even though my contributions are small relative to the scale of the world’s big problems, I think it’s important to do what I can.</p> <p>In the past, I’ve donated to <a href="https://www.unicefusa.org/">UNICEF</a>, <a href="https://oceanconservancy.org/">Ocean Conservancy</a>, and <a href="https://earthjustice.org/">Earthjustice</a>. This year, two main issues have been on my mind. First, the suffering caused by multiple ongoing wars, and second, climate change. 2024 was once again the hottest year on record by global average surface temperature. We have now exceeded the 1.5C degrees of warming target set by the Paris Agreement. (Source: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2025/jan/10/world-temperature-in-2024-exceeded-15c-for-first-time">The Guardian</a>)</p> <p><img src="../../../assets/img/2025-01-12/guardian_global_temp_graph_2024.png" alt="internalimg" style="max-width:800px"/></p> <p>This year, I chose three organizations to donate to:</p> <p><strong>1. Doctors without Borders</strong> <a href="https://www.doctorswithoutborders.org/">(link)</a></p> <p>I wanted to help the people suffering due to violent conflict in Gaza, Sudan, Ukraine, and elsewhere. In addition, Doctors without Borders is addressing the very real <a href="https://www.doctorswithoutborders.org/what-we-do/focus/climate-change-emergency">health impacts of climate change</a>, due to climate-related disasters, malnutrition, and disease.</p> <p><strong>2. Climate Justice Alliance</strong> <a href="https://climatejusticealliance.org/cja-rec2.eives-50-million-thriving-communities/">(link)</a></p> <p>I was looking for an organization that focused on environmental justice, a topic that I studied heavily at Williams-Mystic. Back then, I wrote a policy brief (described <a href="/blog/2024/wm-academics/">here</a>) for which I interviewed Chief Devon Parfait of the Grand Caillou/Dulac Band of Biloxi-Chitimacha-Choctaw. We discussed the local solutions his community is implementing in southern Louisiana, such as building a community center that doubles as a storm shelter and restoring wetlands damaged by oil extraction and storms. When I asked what policy changes would help, he identified the complexity of applying for government grants and then meeting all the subsequent administrative requirements as a major burden. While large nonprofit organizations are able to hire people for this purpose, small local groups can’t afford to do so. The end result is that communities that already possess few resources don’t get the funding they need. In places that have faced environmental racism (like placing polluting facilities in mostly nonwhite communities), this is just one more obstacle.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Grants take up so much of my plate. If I had the money and resources to do all the work I wanted, I would not have the capacity to do it.”</p> <p>– Chief Devon Parfait</p> </blockquote> <p>Climate Justice Alliance addresses this issue by helping small grassroots environmental justice organizations access funds. While reading about the organization, I also heard concerning news: The EPA promised $50 million in Inflation Reduction Act funds to Climate Justice Alliance in 2023, to be distributed to local groups, but the money has still not come through. With the incoming Trump administration determined to <a href="https://insideclimatenews.org/news/01122024/epa-environmental-justice-grant-funding-concerns/">“choke off” environmental justice funding</a>, things are not looking good. I tried <a href="https://win.newmode.net/climatejusticealliance/ejfundsnow">sending a message to the Acting EPA Administrator</a>, but we don’t know if the funds will come through. Nevertheless, I’m donating the small amount I can contribute to the work that they do.</p> <p><strong>3. Giving Green</strong> <a href="https://www.givinggreen.earth/post/giving-green-fund-2024-priorities">(link)</a></p> <p>A many-sided problem like climate change requires many solutions. This organization directs funds to projects like decreasing emissions from heavy industry and livestock, advancing geothermal energy, and supporting the energy transition in low- and middle-income countries. Technology will not absolve us of the need to make systemic changes to society, but technology does have a crucial role to play. This <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LxgMdjyw8uw">video by Kurzgesagt</a> explains that recent advancements in clean energy tech (solar, wind, and batteries) have far exceeded our expectations, placing clean energy at a clear economic advantage over fossil fuels. Further technological advancements will hasten our transition away from fossil fuels.</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Happy New Year! Every January since I started making money, I’ve donated some of it. Even though my contributions are small relative to the scale of the world’s big problems, I think it’s important to do what I can.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taking personal action for the climate</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/my-climate-actions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking personal action for the climate"/><published>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/my-climate-actions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2025/my-climate-actions/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently wrote a post about <a href="/blog/2025/donations-for-climate/">how I’m donating for the climate this year</a>. I also want to talk about changes I’m making in my own life to address the climate crisis.</p> <p>First, I would like to remind everyone that the impact of your individual carbon footprint is negligible compared to the scale of the problem. That’s why we should focus on systemic policy changes, like transitioning to clean energy on a nationwide scale. This <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yiw6_JakZFc">video by Kurzgesagt</a> provides a good overview.</p> <p>That means you shouldn’t spend too much time feeling guilty about personal choices like driving gas-powered cars and buying products that aren’t “green,” especially if the more environmentally friendly option isn’t realistic for you right now. I grew up in a neighborhood where cars were absolutely necessary; there was basically no such thing as public transit and many roads had no sidewalks or pedestrian crossings. If you’re a homeowner, you could install an electric vehicle charging station in your garage, but if you’re a renter, you wouldn’t have consistent access to a charging station. The infrastructure for clean transportation simply isn’t there yet in most places. I’d love to change that, but that will take time.</p> <p>That said, I’m still taking steps to reduce my own carbon footprint. I believe in “doing what you can,” even if it’s small. I also find that changing my everyday habits inspires me to view climate action as an important part of my life. I think a lot about the book <a href="https://jamesclear.com/atomic-habits"><em>Atomic Habits</em></a> by James Clear, which says that your actions inform your identity, which then shapes your actions. You can take advantage of this self-reinforcing loop to change your habits.</p> <blockquote> <p>“It is a simple two-step process:</p> <ol> <li>Decide the type of person you want to be.</li> <li>Prove it to yourself with small wins.”</li> </ol> <p>-James Clear, <em>Atomic Habits</em></p> </blockquote> <p>I’ve started thinking of myself as a person who cares a lot about the climate. As an example, I’ve mostly stopped cooking meat at home, although I still eat it in restaurants or when other people cook. The reasons are several:</p> <ul> <li>Meat, especially beef, causes a lot of carbon emissions and environmental damage</li> <li>It’s healthier to eat less meat and more vegetables</li> <li>Factory farming is pretty unethical</li> <li>Vegetarian and vegan people in my life have made it seem less scary to not eat meat</li> </ul> <p>That last point is pretty crucial. I’ve found that my view of what’s “normal” or appropriate is largely shaped by the views of the people around me. In turn, I’ve realized that changing my behavior also has an effect on the people who know me. Maybe, after being around me, they’ll spend a little more time thinking about the climate. That kind of ripple effect is powerful.</p> <p>Beyond my everyday personal choices (less meat, less single-use plastics, taking the bus), I’m thinking about what I can do to advance the larger systemic changes that we really need. So far, it’s starting small, like writing a letter to my elected officials. I could see myself getting involved more heavily in political advocacy, although as a pretty introverted person, the idea is daunting. I’m also thinking hard about my career path, and how I can use my skills as a computer scientist/biologist for the climate.</p> <p>I’ll continue to think and write about what I can do for the climate. I’m hopeful that I can do my part in bringing us toward a fossil fuel-free future.</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently wrote a post about how I’m donating for the climate this year. I also want to talk about changes I’m making in my own life to address the climate crisis.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The healing power of placentas, smart insulin, and the woman who could smell Parkinson’s</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2024/placentas-smart-insulin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The healing power of placentas, smart insulin, and the woman who could smell Parkinson’s"/><published>2024-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2024/placentas-smart-insulin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2024/placentas-smart-insulin/"><![CDATA[<p>I have a backlog of interesting science stories to share, so here are a few medical miracles for you.</p> <p>   </p> <h2 id="the-woman-who-could-smell-parkinsons"><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/06/14/magazine/parkinsons-smell-disease-detection.html?unlocked_article_code=1.TE4.HEHe.3_86rurHOXJr&amp;smid=url-share">The Woman Who Could Smell Parkinson’s</a></h2> <p>(<em>The New York Times</em>, with gift link!)</p> <p>Read the full article because it’s a fascinating story, but here’s a quick hook:</p> <p>Joy had always had a sensitive nose. One day, she noticed a sudden change in her husband’s smell; years later, he was diagnosed with Parkinson’s. When she accompanied him to a Parkinson’s support group, she noticed that every person with Parkinson’s in the room smelled exactly like her husband.</p> <p>     </p> <h2 id="her-face-was-unrecognizable-after-an-explosion-a-placenta-restored-it"><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/10/08/well/placenta-donations-burns-wounds.html?unlocked_article_code=1.RE4.uNNE.j60u0dohZbPr&amp;smid=url-share">Her Face Was Unrecognizable After an Explosion. A Placenta Restored It.</a></h2> <p>(<em>The New York Times</em>, with gift link!)</p> <p>The placenta, an organ that supplies nutrients to a developing fetus, is typically thrown out after birth. But in this case, the amniotic membrane from a donated placenta was used to repair the skin of a burn victim, with miraculous results. Though we’ve known about this technique since at least 1910, it’s not common practice today.</p> <p>What’s so special about placentas?</p> <ul> <li>Placentas are “immunologically privileged”: this means placental grafts are not rejected by the host immune system after a transplant! (This is related to the fact that the placenta prevents the maternal immune system from attacking the fetus during pregnancy.)</li> <li>Placental tissue produces signaling molecules, including cytokines and growth factors, that urge other cells towards healing and regrowth. Placental grafts have been used to treat chronic wounds that won’t otherwise heal. (<a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC8290337/">PubMed article</a>)</li> </ul> <p>     </p> <h2 id="smart-insulin-switches-itself-off-in-response-to-low-blood-sugar"><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-03286-5">Smart insulin switches itself off in response to low blood sugar</a></h2> <p>People with type 1 diabetes inject insulin to lower their blood glucose, but they run the risk of lowering it too much. A new insulin molecule has been invented that switches itself off when blood glucose levels are too low! It hasn’t been tested in humans yet, but the possibility is exciting.</p> <p><img src="../../../assets/img/2024-10-17/smart_insulin_figure_1.webp" alt="smart-insulin" style="max-width:400px"/></p> <p><strong>Figure 1 | A glucose-responsive insulin for diabetes. a</strong>, In people with type 1 diabetes, the pancreas is not able to produce insulin to counteract the increase in blood glucose that occurs after eating. To reduce the harmful long-term consequences of high blood glucose, insulin can be injected to lower blood glucose through uptake by fat and muscle tissue, and prevention of glucose synthesis by the liver. However, injected insulin remains active even once glucose levels are back to normal, potentially causing a drop to dangerously low levels (hypoglycaemia).</p> <p><strong>b</strong>, Hoeg-Jensen et al. designed a glucose-sensitive insulin called NNC2215, consisting of an insulin backbone, a glucose-binding macrocycle (ring-shaped molecule) and a glucoside (glucose-derived molecule). At high glucose concentrations, glucose binds to the macrocycle, putting NNC2215 into an open conformation that enables it to bind to the insulin receptor to exert its biological effects.</p> <p><strong>c</strong>, At low glucose concentrations, the glucoside occupies the macrocycle, putting NNC2215 into a closed conformation and lowering its activity.</p> <p>(Image and caption: <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-03286-5">Nature</a>)</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="biology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A compilation of stories from medicine]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A lab of one’s own</title><link href="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2024/a-lab-of-ones-own/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A lab of one’s own"/><published>2024-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2024/a-lab-of-ones-own</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alyssa-lee.github.io/blog/2024/a-lab-of-ones-own/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I attended a Women in Science symposium at my workplace. The research presentations were interesting, but the best part was getting to talk to other women scientists. At lunch, I ended up sitting at a table with four women PIs (principal investigators, or PhD scientists running their own labs) and listened to them talk.</p> <p>What really struck me was how much they were <em>there</em> for each other. It reminded me of my experience studying computer science at Carnegie Mellon, where I found an amazing group of women in CS. They understood what it was like to be dismissed by a male classmate, or to feel like an imposter in a field full of men. Having supportive peers and mentors is crucial to success in any discipline, and especially so when you are a woman in a place where women haven’t always been welcomed.</p> <p>I also recently read <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/A-Lab-of-Ones-Own/Rita-Colwell/9781501181290"><em>A Lab of One’s Own</em></a> by Rita Colwell, PhD, a woman scientist who has led a fascinating life.</p> <p><img src="../../../assets/img/2024-09-20/a-lab-of-ones-own.jpg" alt="a lab of ones own book cover" style="max-width:400px"/></p> <blockquote> <p>Rita Colwell is one of the top scientists in America: the groundbreaking microbiologist who discovered how cholera survives between epidemics and the former head of the National Science Foundation. But when she first applied for a graduate fellowship in bacteriology, she was told, “We don’t waste fellowships on women.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Colwell’s life story is incredible. Here’s the story behind her groundbreaking research on cholera: Cholera is a deadly disease caused by <em>Vibrio cholerae</em> bacteria. Scientists have known since 1854 that cholera can spread through sewage-contaminated water. What remained puzzling was where <em>Vibrio cholerae</em> lived between epidemics. Cholera tends to occur in sporadic outbreaks. But no one had found <em>Vibrio cholerae</em> living inside a healthy person when there was no epidemic, and the bacteria died quickly if removed from the human gut. So how did it survive until the next outbreak?</p> <p>Colwell had studied marine microbiology in graduate school. She began to suspect that <em>Vibrio cholerae</em> was capable of living in salt water, like the marine bacteria she knew so well. Colwell followed her hunch and eventually found disease-causing <em>Vibrio cholerae</em> living in the Chesapeake Bay and an estuary in Bangladesh. Her discovery went so radically against the prevailing view on cholera at the time that it took decades for her work to be fully accepted by other scientists in her field. She faced mockery and dismissal many times along the way.</p> <p>Colwell writes of that experience:</p> <blockquote> <p>To this day, I do not believe that I– or my students– would have been treated with the same disdain had I been a man. When people ask me how I had time to publish more than eight hundred scientific papers over the course of my career, I tell them I had no choice: as a woman, I had to prove my findings twenty times over just to get them taken seriously.</p> </blockquote> <p>Her book is full of inspiring stories as well: those who supported her (women and non-women) and other women scientists who pushed for fair treatment. She has a fascinating story about her role in investigating the 2001 anthrax attacks. She discusses her work as head of the National Science Foundation and provides advice for aspiring scientists who would follow in her footsteps.</p> <p>The scientific community can only lose when people are pushed out by discrimination of <em>any</em> kind. I’ll continue to be inspired by those like Rita Colwell who paved the way for my generation of scientists to thrive.</p> <p><a href="../../">back to blog</a></p> <p>     </p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="biology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Women in science, and an awesome memoir by Rita Colwell, PhD]]></summary></entry></feed>